Okay, today's דף Daf is מ"א, Mem Aleph, גיטין Gittin 41. We
pick up on the bottom of מ' ע"ב Mem Amud Bet where
it starts with the משנה Mishna and we're in the middle of
a discussion of things that the rabbis instituted for תיקון עולם, Tikun
Olam, for the betterment of the world and particularly with the focus
on slaves. And the משנה Mishna reads as follows: עבד שעשאו רבו
אפותיקי לאחרים, Eved she'asa rabbo apoteki l'acherim, a slave that his master
made him an אפותיקי, apoteki, put a lien on him for others.
So an אפותיקי apoteki is a certain type of a focused lien
that gives the lien holder strong rights to the object of the
אפותיקי, apoteki, but it might also weaken his rights, his ability to
collect from other things. Okay, so now there's a creditor who's a
slave owner, we'll call him ראובן, Reuven, and he owes money to
שמעון, Shimon, and what he does is he says שמעון, Shimon, you
will have your lien, you will have an אפותיקי apoteki on my
slave. You will have the ability to collect your debt from my
slave. Okay, that's what he does.
Now ושחררו, veshichraro, and he freed him, presumably, although we'll see there's
a whole discussion in the גמרא Gemara because this משנה Mishna is
hard to read, who's doing what acts, but we'll read it that
ראובן Reuven now freed the slave. So this slave is now a
free man and now שמעון Shimon is out because שמעון Shimon doesn't
have any property to collect from because he can only collect from
him when he was treated as property, not now that he's a
free man. שורת הדין אין העבד חייב כלום, Shurat hadin ein ha'eved
chayav klum, as a letter of law, the slave has no obligation.
Why should he have an obligation? I mean, ראובן Reuven managed to
avoid paying שמעון Shimon by freeing the slave. So ראובן Reuven maybe
owes something to שמעון Shimon but the slave doesn't owe anything, the
slave is a free man. אלא מפני תיקון עולם, Ella mipnei tikun
olam, but for the sake of תיקון עולם, Tikun Olam, כופין את
רבו ועושה אותו בן חורין, kofin et rabbo ve'oseh oto ben chorin,
you force the master to make him a free person. Now that's
bizarre because it sounds like the master already made him a free
person, so we'll have to figure that out in the גמרא. Gemara.
וכותב שטר על דמיו, Vechotev shtar al damav, and the and the
slave will write a שטר shtar document, a writ of a debt
for his value. So he now has to reimburse his value to,
according to the way of reading this, to שמעון. Shimon. Now that
makes no sense why it should be the slave's responsibility to reimburse
his value to שמעון. Shimon. So this way of reading it we
don't understand why the slave is paying שמעון Shimon and we don't
understand why ראובן Reuven has to rewrite a writ of freedom for
the slave. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר אינו כותב אלא משחרר, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel omer eino kotev ela meshachrer, the slave does not
write the debt, the one who freed him, ראובן, Reuven, has to
now owe שמעון Shimon the money because ראובן Reuven took away the
slave, took away שמעון's Shimon ability to collect from the slave. So
that at least makes sense. But it does not make sense why
the slave should owe the money and it does not make sense
why ראובן Reuven would have to rewrite a writ of freedom. So
now we will see two different ways of reading this משנה Mishna
in the גמרא. Gemara. גמרא: Gemara: עבד שעשאו רבו אפותיקי ושחררו. Eved
she'asa rabbo apoteki veshichraro. מי שחררו? Mi shichraro? Who freed him? Okay,
אמר רב רבו ראשון. Amar Rav rabbo rishon. So the first master,
which is obviously the simple read of the משנה, Mishna, ראובן Reuven
freed him. שורת הדין אין העבד חייב כלום לרבו שני. Shurat hadin
ein ha'eved chayav klum l'rabbo sheni. Now the slave as a matter
of law does not owe anything to the second master, meaning the
person who would have been his second master. He doesn't owe anything
to שמעון. Shimon. Okay, שמעון Shimon lost his right to collect from
the slave and the slave owes nothing to
שמעון. Shimon. Now why did freeing the slave work? Why did freeing
the slave have the effect of שמעון Shimon losing his lien? כדרבא,
Kiderava, this goes like רבא. Rava. דאמר רבא הקדש חמץ ושחרור מפקיעין
מידי שעבוד, D'amar Rava hekdesh chametz veshichrur mafki'in midei shibud, that sanctifying
something, freeing a slave, and חמץ chametz undermines, or removes, destroys any
type of lien that might be on the object. What does this
mean? So there are three cases. Let's take them one by one.
First you have the הקדש, hekdesh, sanctifying. I have let's say, start
with something that would not be a problem. I have a car
or a house and I give שמעון Shimon a lien on it
and then I go ahead and an אפותיקי, apoteki, even a strong
lien, and then I go ahead and I sanctify it to the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So all I've really done is I've transferred
ownership to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. In that case, even though
the object becomes sanctified, it really is anchored in a question of
ownership, who owns it? And the same way that if I had
sold that property to a different person,
שמעון Shimon could come because of his lien and take it from
that other person. If I sell that property and I give that
property or I gift that property to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
they're just another type of an ownership. It brings הקדש hekdesh to
the object, but they're another type of an ownership. It's a question
about property ownership and שמעון Shimon can come and take it and
seize it from the בית המקדש's Beis HaMikdash ownership because of his
lien. Maybe he'll do some pro forma type of redeeming of it
to remove the sanctity of the object, but fundamentally he has rights
because it's a question of who owns it. That's a הקדש hekdesh
that would not remove the lien. But let's say I didn't do
that. Let's say it's a different case. Let's say it's my cow
and I give שמעון Shimon a lien, an אפותיקי apoteki on my
cow, and then I turn the cow and I sanctify it to
the... And I make it an עולה *olah*. The idea that I've
now sanctified it as a sacrifice, it has nothing to do with
who owns the object. Maybe even the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* doesn't
own it, maybe it's mine, it's my עולה *olah*, it's my sacrifice.
It has to do though with the identity of the object. This
object stops being a piece of property, this object is seen of
as a sacrifice, okay, and as such, a sacrifice is not something
that anybody can own and claim ownership over. So the idea, the
lien automatically is destroyed, there's no concept of lien by something that
is actually a sacrifice, קדושת הגוף *kedushat haguf*, by its very identity
is something that is holy, not just happens to be owned by
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. And for the same reason you can't
redeem a sacrifice unless it has a blemish. So it can't, it's
not about ownership and therefore it's fundamentally in a different category, the
sense of liens is, you know, completely falls away. So that would
destroy the liens that שמעון Shimon, *Shimon* would have on it. שחרור
*Shichrur* is another case, same idea. As long as my slave, somebody
is a slave, they're considered הלכתית *halachically* property, and therefore, you know,
if I sold my slave, שמעון Shimon *Shimon* could come and take
it from the purchaser, so שמעון Shimon *Shimon* can, you know, that's
when it's all within the realm of property, those liens are good.
But as soon as I free my slave, he's now a free
man, and the idea that you can have liens on a free
man is inconceivable. It's only something that's considered in the realm of
property.
Sacrifices aren't property and a free person is not property and therefore
the liens fall away. That's the case of שחרור *shichrur*. חמץ *Chametz*
is a little different, but ultimately the same idea. And that's, let's
say a non-Jew has an אפותיקי Apotiki *apotiki*, has liens on my
חמץ *chametz*, and I don't, and comes along פסח *Pesach*. So פסח
*Pesach* makes the חמץ *chametz* אסור בהנאה *assur behana'ah*, forbidden to derive
benefit. So actually I'd be happy if the non-Jew took his liens
and went ahead and collected it, then I'd have paid off my
debt, but I'm not allowed to do that because I can't derive
benefit. But even besides the question of permission to derive benefit, the
fact that something is אסור בהנאה *assur behana'ah* takes it out of
the realm of normal property that can be owned and transferred. The
whole idea about this is something that's like banned and off limits.
So therefore these three things change the fundamental identity of the object
and take it out of the realm of a property that can
have liens. Okay, so that's what רבא *Rava* says, הקדש חמץ ושחרור
מפקיעין מידי שעבוד *hekdesh chametz veshichrur mafki'in miydei shibud*. So that just
explains why the master freed him, was able to free him, he
still had enough ownership to free him, ראובן Reuven, *Reuven*, and now
שמעון Shimon *Shimon* is out and has nothing that has liens on
it and can't collect his debt. Okay, that's the first part of
the משנה Mishnah, *mishna*. Great. אלא Ella, מפני תיקון tikkun, העולם *Ela
mipnei tikkun haolam*, and the slave, why would the slave own anything,
the slave is free, אלא מפני תיקון tikkun העולם שמא ימצאנו בשוק
ויאמר לו עבדי אתה *ela mipnei tikkun haolam shema yimtza'enu bashuk veyomar
lo avdi atah*, but for the sake of the betterment of the
world, lest שמעון Shimon *Shimon* go ahead and find the slave in
the marketplace and claim you're still my slave. So this is a
reasonable concern. Anybody ever saw the movie 12 Years a Slave? You
know, in a society, just because you're free doesn't always mean that
the society will recognize you as such and you'll always be able
to assert or to prove your freedom. So given that שמעון Shimon
*Shimon* had a very strong liens on this slave,
you know, even though ראובן Reuven *Reuven* freed him and successfully freed
him, שמעון Shimon *Shimon* might go ahead and make a claim that
no, I was the owner, I had liens, I had a right,
you're still my slave, and ראובן Reuven *Reuven* owes me the money
and I'm taking you back and I'm taking you, you know, I'm
taking you to serve me, I'm taking you as my slave, and
good luck trying to fight that in the court system, right? Who
do we think really has the power? Okay, so that's a not
unreasonable concern that even after technically being freed, שמעון Shimon *Shimon* who
otherwise would be out his money might want to still claim that
he's still a slave and claim that he is his slave and
seize him in payment of the debt. So what are we going
to do to protect the slave? So כופין את רבו שני ועושה
אותו בן חורין Ben chorin, *kofin et rabo sheni ve'oseh oto ben
chorin*. So now we understand who's writing the writ of freedom. You
force שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, the person who, the person who would purport
to be the second master, he's not really the second master, but
the person who would purport to be the master, you force שמעון
Shimon *Shimon* to write a writ of freedom and therefore שמעון Shimon
*Shimon* will not be able to make any claim that this person
is his slave because שמעון Shimon *Shimon* has already written something that
he is freeing him as a slave. So that protects this slave
from staying a free person. Okay, now, וכותב עבד Eved, שטר shtar
על דמיו *vechotev eved shtar al damav*. And now what we're, what
we're going to have to do maybe, right, to get שמעון Shimon
*Shimon* to go along with it is that in exchange, the slave
now writes an IOU to שמעון Shimon *Shimon* that he owes שמעון
Shimon. *Shimon* his value. Now, that's not fair because, you know, it's
not the slave who did anything wrong, it's ראובן Reuven *Reuven* who
did something wrong to שמעון Shimon *Shimon*. Why should the slave have
to pay שמעון Shimon, *Shimon*? But nevertheless, the rabbis understood that this
was a fair tradeoff for the sake of the slave. Better to
be protected against being claimed to be a slave by somebody who
has more power than you, okay, and exposing yourself to that real
risk, better that That person should
clearly disavow any claim, and in exchange, you're a free person, you'll
have to pay off the debt over time, you'll have to pay
off the debt. So it's not fair, but ultimately it's for the
betterment of the slave. That's what the rabbis say. רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel אומר אין העבד כותב אלא המשחרר כותב.
No, at the end of the day, yes, you know, שמעון, if
we want to get שמעון to write that writ of manumission, he
might have to get somebody to promise to pay him, but that
person is not going to be the slave, it's going to be
ראובן, Reuven which makes sense. ראובן Reuven ultimately was the one who
owed him money. ראובן's Reuven actions prevented שמעון from collecting his debt.
ראובן Reuven has to be the one that now writes him that
'I owe
you'. Okay. במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamifligi? What is their debate of רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and the חכמים Hakhamim about? במזיק שעבודו של חבירו
קמיפלגי. B'mazik shibudo shel havero kamifligi. When you damage your friend's not
property, but your friend's lien, you do something to destroy either the
property that somebody has a lien on or to destroy the lien
itself. Okay. דמר סבר חייב ומר סבר פטור. D'mar savar hayyav u-mar
savar patur. One says you're חייב, hayyav, one says you're פטור. patur.
So if, you know, שמעון had a lien on this house and
I went ahead and I destroyed this house, so okay, maybe there's
a question, you know, I was ראובן's Reuven house. So A, maybe
there's a question do I owe ראובן Reuven any money, but there's
also a question if I owe שמעון money because I've now prevented
שמעון from paying up his debt and his lien might give him
certain property rights, so maybe it's also like I destroyed שמעון's property.
So in this case, ראובן Reuven by freeing the slave, he destroyed
שמעון's lien. Okay, and therefore the question is, he didn't destroy the
property, but he destroyed שמעון's lien. So שמעון had a type of
ownership over the slave, ראובן Reuven acted in a way that essentially
it's like he damaged the property or he damaged the lien itself,
and is that considered a tort and does ראובן Reuven have to
pay? So דמר סבר חייב ומר סבר פטור. D'mar savar hayyav u-mar
savar patur. That רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says ראובן Reuven has to
compensate שמעון for destroying the lien on the slave, and the חכמים
Hakhamim say he doesn't have to compensate. And that's their debate. So
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says ראובן Reuven pays because ראובן Reuven destroyed
the lien and that's a tort and he has to pay him
for it. And so even though שמעון can't collect the first debt,
he can now collect the second debt, and the חכמים Hakhamim say
no, ראובן Reuven is exempt, it'll be the slave who pays it.
Now, you know, that's at least explaining why רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
says as a matter of law ראובן is actually obligated because he
damaged the tort, he damaged, you know, שמעון's property, שמעון's lien.
Even once you say though as a matter of law of tort,
ראובן isn't obligated, it doesn't exactly tell you that the slave should
be the one to pay. Maybe we should still make ראובן pay
because ראובן was to blame, at least blame, you know, in terms
of the hurt of שמעון. He did something good vis-a-vis the slave.
But apparently what the גמרא Gemara is saying is once there's not
an actual tort, if we want שמעון to write this שטר shtar
in order to protect the slave, it makes sense that it will
be the slave that will be the one that will have to
owe the money, and it's ultimately in his benefit. Okay. That's that
debate.
איתמר נמי, Itmar nami, we also taught
a ברייתא, braita, המזיק שעבודו של חבירו, hamazzik shibudo shel havero, באנו
למחלוקת רבן גמליאל ורבנן. banu l'mahloket Rabban Gamliel v'rabanan. That would be
the debate of רבן גמליאל and the rabbis. That's at the core
of their debate. That's one way of reading the משנה, Mishnah, that's
רב's Rav way of reading the משנה, Mishnah, that it is the
first master who freed him and the second master who writes the
writ of manumission in order so he does not make any false
claims against the slave. עולא אמר מי שחררו רבו שני. Ulla amar
mi shihraro rabbo sheni. Now עולא Ulla flips it. Who freed him?
The second master. When it says 'the master freed him,' it meant
the person who would purport to be the master, the person who
would want to take possession of the slave to pay the debt.
So the creditor, שמעון, is the one who quote unquote 'freed him'
or looked like he freed him, he really didn't have the power
to free him, but he wrote this writ of freedom. So רבו
שני שחררו. rabbo sheni shihraro. So שורת הדין אין העבד חייב כלום.
shurat hadin ein ha'eved hayyav klum. The slave as a matter of
law is not obligated, so according to this it doesn't mean he's
not obligated in money, of course he's not obligated in money, you
know, he hasn't even really been freed. So we're going to this
is going to really be the weakest part of this reading of
the משנה, Mishnah. it means he's not obligated in מצוות. mitzvot. He
hasn't yet been freed. Okay. That's a very weak read of the
משנה. Mishnah The משנה Mishna seems to be talking about who do
you have to pay, but the גמרא Gemara is reading it as
the second master or the creditor quote unquote freed him and the
slave is not yet free. Okay. אלא, so now what do you
do? מפני תיקון עולם, mipne tikkun olam, for the sake of the
betterment of the world, meaning nothing really happened, but now we've got
a problem. שמא יצא עליו שם בן חורין. shema yatza alav shem
ben horin. There is now a perception, you know, a report that
this person is a free man. So the second person was the
creditor, he possibly was a party presumably with wealth and with power,
and you know he's going around and he's saying 'I'm going to
collect that slave' and then he frees him, people are under the
perception that this slave has been freed. Now that's not good for
society because then the slave will, you know, marry a Jewish woman,
then the marriage won't be binding and we'll think he's obligated in
מצוות mitzvot and he's not fully obligated in מצוות. mitzvot. So we've
got a
problem: the
perception. So what the חכמים Chachamim are going to do now to
fix this that we've got this problem that of the perception reality
is they're going to not work to fix the perception, they're going
to work to fix the reality, the facts. So what do we
do?
כופין את רבו ראשון ועושהו בן חורין. Kofin es rabo rishon ve'oso
ben chorin. You force the first master, Reuven, the guy who really
owns him, you force him to free him to turn the perception
to turn you know what the facts to be the same as
the perception. Okay? וכותב שטר על דמיו. Vechoseiv shtar al damav. ועושהו
בן חורין וכותב שטר על דמיו. Ve'oso ben chorin vechoseiv shtar al
damav. Now, the slave just got freed. He wasn't deserving to get
freed. I mean, whatever deserving means, but it wasn't sort of going
to be a reality, just you know, this yahoo Shimon tried to
free him, but that didn't mean anything. Now we're going to make
the master Reuven free him, so the slave got freed. The slave
now has to pay back
Reuven. And presumably this is a very good deal for a slave.
If you tell any slave you'll be free as of today and
but eventually over time you'll have to pay back the debt, I'm
sure they would have taken up that offer. Okay? So that's what
we do. We make Reuven free him to match the to make
the reality match the perception, and the slave then will now pay
back Reuven. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר אינו כותב אלא משחרר כותב.
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer eino koseiv ela meshachrer koseiv. No, the
slave doesn't pay, Shimon pays. It's all Shimon's fault, so Shimon is
going to be the one that is going to pay back Reuven.
Now, you might be saying, why does Shimon have to pay Reuven?
Reuven was the one who owed Shimon money. But as רש"י Rashi
explains, in case the slave is worth more. Let's say the debt
was eight hundred and the slave was worth a thousand. So had
Shimon seized the slave, he would have had to pay Reuven back
two hundred. Now what Shimon did is Shimon freed the slave quote-unquote
freed the slave, Reuven actually freed him, so Reuven was forced to
free him, Reuven is now out a thousand for a debt of
eight hundred, Shimon now has to give him back the difference of
the two hundred. The debt is paid and Shimon gives him back
the two hundred. Okay, so that's the question: Does the slave pay
Reuven, maybe also the slave would only pay two hundred since Shimon
quote-unquote freed him, the debt is over? Okay, but does the slave
pay Reuven or does Shimon pay Reuven for those for that two
hundred? Okay, so now what is this debate about? אלא משחרר כותב.
Ela meshachrer koseiv. ומאי קמיפלגי? Umai kamiflagi? What are they debating? בהיזק
שאינו ניכר קמיפלגי. Behezek she'eino nikkar kemiflagi. With a damage that is
not you know obvious, that is not visible. מר סבר שמיה היזק,
Mar savar shemeh hezek, one says it's considered damage, ומר סבר לא
שמיה היזק, umar savar lo shemeh hezek, it's not considered damage. What's
the non-visible damage? Well, Shimon made the slave into a free person,
so he basically removed Reuven's ownership, he damaged Reuven's property, he took
this property and made it no longer his property. Okay, but it's
not exactly the damage is not exactly visible. Now, it's a little
bit of a question, I mean תוספות Tosafos says, really it's not
visible? I mean, somebody's walking around as a free person as opposed
to walking around as a slave, you know, there's a degree of
visibility there,
number one. Number two is, is the problem really the question of
visibility or the problem is that Shimon really didn't even do anything?
He didn't actually do the damage, he said some words or he
gave a שטר shtar. that didn't have any effect that then led
the rabbis to force Reuven to go out and free him. Okay,
so maybe it's not so much that it's not visible as that
it's indirect. But anyway, that's the question. Through Shimon's action, Reuven now
no longer owns the slave. Is Shimon liable or not for that
damage that he did to Reuven's property? Okay, so מר סבר שמיה
היזק ומר סבר לא שמיה היזק. Mar savar shemeh hezek umar savar
lo shemeh hezek. So if you say like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel it is damage, so Shimon caused Reuven's property
to be lost, to be damaged quote-unquote, and therefore Shimon pays the
difference, the extra two hundred dollars. If you say Shimon did not
damage, it's not a tort that can be collected, the damage he
did to the slave, then we are going to have, look again
it was all because of Shimon, we're going to have the slave
bear the burden of it. This is like the previous one, if
you don't have a tort on Reuven and Shimon, then because the
slave is getting freed and because we're protecting the interests of the
slave, the slave is now going to be the one to owe
the money. Okay, so that is the two ways of reading it
between רב Rav and עולא. Ulla. According to רב Rav it is
the first master that freed the slave, the second master goes ahead
and writes a writ in order to so to not falsely claim
the slave is his, and then it's the question of you know
of who pays back Shimon. According to the second read, it's Shimon
freed
the slave quote-unquote freed the slave, Reuven now has to make the
facts match the perception, and the question is now going to be
who pays back Reuven. All right. Now, the גמרא Gemara says like
this: עולא מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב? Ulla mai ta'ama lo amar
kerav? Why did עולא Ulla not say like רב Rav that it
was the first master who genuinely freed the slave? אמר לך סיפא
רבו קרי ליה? Amar lach seifa rabo kari leh? Because the משנה
Mishnah when it continues, it says the master, you know, writes a
writ of freedom, and how can How can you call שמעון *Shimon*
the master? He's not the master; he's the one who's purporting to
be the master,
who would falsely claim to be the master, but the משנה Mishnah.
*Mishnah* wouldn't call him the master. So that's therefore I don't like
your read because you're having the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* call שמעון *Shimon*
the guy who's writing the the writ, who's the master, you know,
you're having that be שמעון *Shimon*. Okay. רבו קרי ליה *Rabo kari
lei*? ורב מאי טעמא לא אמר כעולא *VeRav mai ta'ama lo amar
k'Ulla*? אמר לך *Amar lach*: שני משחרר קרי ליה *sheini meshacher kari
lei*. It's the other part of the משנה mishna *Mishnah* that's the
problem. Because then the משנה *Mishnah* says that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel* says the freer, the
one who freed him, has to pay, and you know, you say
that that means that שמעון *Shimon* has to pay, but שמעון *Shimon*
didn't really free him, ראובן *Reuven* freed him, שמעון *Shimon* just pretended
to free him. Bottom line is both רב *Rav* and עולא *Ulla*
have to read in.
The משנה *Mishnah* here speaks about the master and the one who
frees him. And the only person who's both really the master and
really the one who's freed him is ראובן *Reuven*. But the משנה
*Mishnah* doesn't make sense unless you read שמעון *Shimon* into one of
those roles. So that makes it hard to read the משנה *Mishnah*
either way because either you're going to have to read שמעון *Shimon*
into the master or into the freer, and he's not genuinely either.
Okay. So the so the משנה *Mishnah* is a hard read, it's
a harder read I should say according to עולא *Ulla* that has
to say slave isn't liable means a slave isn't isn't isn't obligated
in מצות *mitzvot*. That's a very difficult read. Okay. But anyway, two
different reads of the משנה *Mishnah*. Now that we're talking about אפותיקי
Apotiki *apotiki* we're going to continue to discuss the power and the
nature of this lien called an אפותיקי *apotiki*. So, איתמר *itmar*: it
was taught העושה שדהו אפותיקי לאחרים *ha'oseh sadeh apotiki l'acherim*.
Somebody goes ahead and makes his field, he puts it he makes
an אפותיקי *apotiki* on his field for a creditor. He gives this
creditor this strong lien, this אפותיקי *apotiki*. ושטפה נהר *Veshatfah nahar*. And
then it gets swamped by a river and it's underwater and it's
completely worthless. אמר אימי שפיר נאה *Amar Immi Shafir Noeh*... אימי שפיר
נאה *Immi Shafir Noeh*. This person, Rabbi by the name of אימי
שפיר נאה *Immi Shafir Noeh*, which means of of pleasant visage, of
like like good looking, אמר רבי Rabbi יוחנן *amar Rabbi Yochanan*: אינו
גובה משאר נכסים *eino goveh mishar nechasim*.
So the question here is like this: the אפותיקי *apotiki* gives you
a focused and strong lien on the property that the אפותיקי *apotiki*
is for, does it you know like limit your rights to the
other to other property as well? Does it does it mean you
have no liens on anything else? So in the here this אימי
שפיר נאה *Immi Shafir Noeh* says in the name of רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan*, it limits you. It's exclusive. You only you have an
intense right to this property and no rights to anything else. So
if you can't collect from this property you're out. That's sort of
what the משנה *Mishnah* sounded like in terms of the slave. ואבוה
דשמואל אמר גובה משאר נכסים *Va'avuah deShmuel amar goveh mishar nechasim*. No,
no, no. You can if you can't maybe you have to collect
from this first, okay, maybe that's what it does, it prioritizes that
and it gives you more rights to that, but it doesn't prevent
you from collecting from other property. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק משום
דאימי שפיר נאה הוא אמר שמעתא דלא שפירן *Amar Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak mishum de'Immi Shafir Noeh hu amar shema'ata d'lo shaphiran*. So he
makes a little he's being a little sarcastic. רב נחמן בר יצחק
*Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak* says because אימי *Immi* is of is so
good looking, he says ideas, הלכות *halachot* that are not so attractive.
Like he didn't like this idea. Why should because you strengthen somebody's
lien, why should that prevent the person from collecting from other things?
So that he didn't like. So so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
אלא *ela* לתירגם שמעתיה *letargem shema'atei* דאמר ליה לא יהא פרעון אלא
מזה *d'amar lei lo yehe pira'on ela mizu*. So the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* says you know what you're right. The way to understand what
אימי *Immi* was saying in the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*,
and maybe they weren't even debating, was that that if you make
it a super strong, you are explicit, you make it exclusive, explicitly
exclusive, and you say you can only collect from this, so in
that case you are explicitly
limiting,
eliminating, excluding any liens on any of the rest of the property.
So you have a normal set of liens, which are you know
not an אפותיקי *apotiki*, which means that there's a whole question about
which one do you choose and like you don't have any particular
right to any one of them, okay, so it's more sort of
diffuse, but that would be a normal lien. Then you have an
אפותיקי *apotiki* what's called סתם *stam*, which is you just say this
is an אפותיקי *apotiki*, which means that you have stronger rights to
this, maybe you take you have rights to it before anybody else,
you know, maybe if the owner tries to sell it you can
immediately annul the sale, we'll sort of see things like that, okay,
but it also means that if you can't collect from this, you
can go to other things. And then you have an אפותיקי מפורש
*apotiki meforash*, an explicit אפותיקי *apotiki*, which means this is the only
thing you can collect from. Okay. תניא אידך *Tanya idach* we taught
now
I'm sorry תניא נמי הכי *tanya nami hachi* we taught similarly in
a ברייתא Braisa. *braitah*: העושה שדהו אפותיקי לאחר ושטפה נהר גובה משאר
נכסים *ha'oseh sadeh apotiki l'acher veshatfah nahar goveh mishar nechasim*. If you
made your שדה *sadeh* an אפותיקי *apotiki* to somebody else and it
was swamped by a river, you can go ahead and collect, so
if you can't collect from this you can collect from others. ואם
אמר לו לא יהא לך פרעון אלא מזה *Ve'im amar lo lo
yehe lach pira'on ela mizu*, but if he said explicitly you can
you will be nowhere else to collect from except this, this is
the only thing you have a lien on, then in that case
אינו גובה משאר נכסים *eino goveh mishar nechasim*, you cannot collect from
from others. תניא אידך *Tanya idach* now we taught in fine that's
so there you go exactly that distinction. תניא אידך *Tanya idach* תניא
אידך, we've done another ברייתא. Braita. העושה שדהו אפותיקי לבעל חוב או
לכתובת אשה גובה משאר נכסים. Haoseh sadehu apotiki l'baal chov o l'ksuvas
isha goveh mishar nechasim. If you make your field an אפותיקי for
a creditor or for your wife's כתובה, Kesuvah, then and they can
collect from other property presumably if they're not able to collect from
this or they you know presumably let's say they have to go
to this first but if that's not sufficient they can go to
other property. So that's what we've already taught but now we're going
to have a distinction about the כתובה Kesuvah according to רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר בעל
חוב גובה משאר נכסים. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer baal chov goveh
mishar nechasim. I agree with you with the בעל חוב. Baal chov.
אשה אינה גובה משאר נכסים. Isha einah govah mishar nechasim. But the
wife cannot collect from other property. Why not? שאין דרכה של אשה
לחזר אחר בתי דינין. She'ein darchah shel isha l'chazer achar batei dinin.
Because it is not the way of a woman to go having
to you know go sue the person in court and have to
you know find court records and discover where all your property is
and all the possible people you sold it to. Now that's all
very nice but that sounds like it sounds like you're trying to
be considerate of her and saying that since you know women are
not usually in the whole court system and they can't be expected
to trace the paper trail of all of your things we're going
to make it easier for her and say that she only collects
from this one thing. But like is that really easier? I mean
you're excluding her ability to get from other things. So you know
תוספות Tosfos discusses this and תוספות Tosfos also speaks about well it
does strengthen her ability because it means that any attempt to sell
this thing she can immediately void. So therefore it allows her to
focus on this one thing and to make sure that this one
thing is not sold and that actually will be is seen to
be in her ultimately in her benefit. Okay that at least is
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל's position. Okay so that's in terms of the
idea of אפותיקי and the תיקון עולם Tikkun olam about somebody who
was freed but might not be perceived of as being freed or
might be claimed to have not been freed. Now we move to
another משנה about a slave and this is a very famous משנה.
Okay מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן חורין. Mi shechatzyo eved vechatzyo ben
chorin. Somebody half slave half free. How is this possible? We'll discuss
in the גמרא Gemara but the simplest way is that he was
owned by two partners and one partner freed him. So therefore this
person now is considered to be a half slave half free man.
The interesting thing is as we were discussing before you know that
this question is not just a question of ownership. Do does somebody
else own me or do I own myself? The part of me
that has been freed is a fundamentally different identity and a different
legal status. It's the legal status of a בן חורין, a free
man and not of an עבד, a slave, which has a different
level of obligation in מצוות. Mitzvos. I'm able to marry a Jewish
woman as a free man, I'm not able to do so as
a slave, I'm permitted to marry a Jewish woman and not permitted
as a slave. So you might have you know it's funny that
we can allow for this dual status. You might feel like you
know a status has to be one. You're either a slave or
a free man, you can't be half and half. Those are contradictory
statuses but that actually הלכה Halacha allows for. And that's going to
lead to the interesting question in this משנה. So you have this
slave that half free half slave half free half slave. מי שחציו
עבד וחציו בן חורין. Mi shechatzyo eved vechatzyo ben chorin. עובד את
רבו יום אחד ואת עצמו יום אחד. Oved es rabo yom echad
v'es atzmo yom echad. דברי בית הלל. Divrei Beis Hillel. So בית
הלל Beis Hillel just focuses on the monetary aspects, right? I'm entitled
to my own earnings half of my own earnings because of the
half of me that's freed and my master's entitled to half of
my own earnings. Half the time I can tell myself where you
know what I'm going to do go and what I'm going to
do and half of the you know my master gets to tell
me. So we'll alternate days. It works that שבת Shabbos I'm off.
So therefore you know you have an even number of days and
one day I'll work for my master and I'll be under his
control and he gets to keep my earnings and one day I'll
be under my control and I'll keep my earnings. That's what בית
הלל Beis Hillel says. בית שמאי אומרים תיקנתם את רבו ואת עצמו
לא תיקנתם. Beis Shammai omrim tikantam es rabo v'es atzmo lo tikantam.
You and here's the word of תיקון עולם, Tikkun olam, you have
fixed his master, meaning you've taken care of his master. His master
has rights to half his earnings and you've ensured that his master
gets half his earnings. But you haven't taken care of the slave
because there's more to the slave than just half of his earnings.
Okay לישא שפחה אי אפשר שכבר חציו בן חורין. Lisha shifcha i
efshar shekvar chatzyo ben chorin. He might be able to keep his
earnings but what about getting married? He can't marry a שפחה, Shifcha,
a slave, because half of him is a free man and
a normal you know Jewish man is not allowed to marry a
non-Jewish slave. It's learned from the פסוק Pasuk of לא יהיה קדשה.
lo yiheyeh kadeshah. בת חורין אי אפשר שכבר חציו עבד. Bas chorin
i efshar shekvar chatzyo eved. Now he can't marry a free woman
because the half of him that is a slave. לא יקדש Lo
yekadesh is the basis that we say that a free that a
a Jewish woman cannot marry a male slave. Okay so therefore he
is prohibited to getting married. So you are not giving him his
full life even though you are giving him his
פרנסה. Parnasa.
Okay now יבטל, Yibatel, so maybe say okay don't have you know
don't have kids. ולאו לא נברא העולם אלא לפרייה ורבייה. V'lo lo
nivra haolam ela l'pirya v'rivya. But you that's not a solution because
the world was created for the sake of procreation. שנאמר לא תהו
בראה לשבת יצרה. Shene'emar lo sohu bera'ah lasheves yetzarah. I didn't create
the world to lay to be to be void and empty, it
was fashioned in order to be settled. אלא מפני תיקון עולם. Ela
mipnei tikkun olam. For the sake of תיקון עולם. Tikkun olam. And
here it's very nice you know you have the word this might
have been the original form of the word תיקון עולם. Tikkun olam.
It says תיקנתם. Tikantam. תקנתם את רבו, tikkantem et rabbo, עצמו לא
תקנתם, atzmo lo tikkantem, לא נברא העולם. lo nivra ha'olam.
So due to the תיקון, not just for the slave, the master,
but the תיקון of the עולם, olam, כופין את רבו ומוציאו בן
חורין. kofin et rabbo umotzi'o ben chorin.
You force the master to free him and now he can go
ahead and get married, he's a total free person. וכותב שטר חצי
דמיו, vekotev shtar chatzi damav, and the slave has to owe the
master half of his value. He has to pay back the master
for the cost of the other half of him. וחזרו בית הלל
להורות כדברי בית שמאי. vechazru Beit Hillel lehorot k'divrei Beit Shammai. בית
הלל Beit Hillel was persuaded and then they went back to rule
like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Now first of all that's fascinating because
we always assume like, you know, בית הלל Beit Hillel are the
sympathetic, they're the, you know, the nice guys, the responsive to the
human condition, so it's quite fascinating and I don't have an explanation
but here it seems to reverse itself and eventually בית הלל Beit
Hillel came along to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. The other interesting thing
is why the משנה quoted the reason of לא תהו בראה lo
tohu bera'ah and not the idea of
the
מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו. peru urvu. So this is an important
discussion that תוספות Tosafot has, and תוספות Tosafot says, look, if it
was just for פרו ורבו, peru urvu, you could say that's not
enough. I mean somebody is an אונס, oness, somebody's not able to
fulfill a מצוה, mitzvah, okay, you know, so let's say, I mean,
let's say you would say the slave, I don't know, can't sit
in a סוכה, sukkah, would that be a reason to free the
slave? Sometimes there's מצוות mitzvot we can't do and it's not our
fault and God isn't going to hold us responsible. So that's why
בית שמאי Beit Shammai had to say it's not just the מצוה
mitzvah of פרו ורבו, peru urvu, it's that this is such a
huge מצוה, mitzvah, forget even the technical question, am I obligated, not
obligated, did I fulfill it, am I פטור patur or not, you
know, it's fundamental to the human condition and to the reason the
world was created, and that is something such a big מצוה, mitzvah,
such a big, you know, human fulfillment that you're withholding from him,
that is not acceptable. If he's fully a slave, he could be
married and have kids, now he can't do either, that is something
that we have to fix. Okay. And therefore that, so that's what
they say, and from that perspective, you know, it's sort of telling
you the weight of the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו, peru urvu,
but it's also telling you that there's this fundamental concept that goes
beyond the question of is it a מצוה mitzvah or not a
מצוה. mitzvah. And that does lead to a whole interesting discussion in
תוספות Tosafot that maybe the side of him that's a slave isn't
obligated in פרו ורבו, peru urvu, the side that's a slave has
the same level of obligations as a woman, but maybe that side
is obligated, maybe there's this obligation called לא תהו בראה lo tohu
bera'ah or לשבת. lashevet. So תוספות Tosafot develops this idea that gets
developed more in later הלכה halacha that there's this מצוה mitzvah called
לשבת lashevet that applies to women and to slaves and turns this
sense of this profound importance, you know, the purpose of creation, etc.,
and somewhat halachicizes it and makes it into a מצוה mitzvah that
now applies, you know, to women and slaves. But you don't have
to say any of that, you just have to say that this
is such a powerful value that we have to, and it underlies
the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו, peru urvu, that we have to
do something for the sake of the slave. Okay, let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught. המשחרר חצי עבדו. hamishachrer chatzi
avdo. Now, I gave the example, רש"י Rashi said already, that it
was half owned by partners and one partner freed and the other
did not. The גמרא Gemara is now going to discuss, how can
you create a half slave half free person? Can you do it
with a single owner to get to that reality? A single owner
owns a whole slave, can he free half of him? המשחרר חצי
עבדו, hamishachrer chatzi avdo,
somebody tries to free half his slave, רבי
אומר קנה, Rabbi omer kana, he, it acquires, meaning the slave acquires
half of himself, he's half free now. וחכמים אומרים לא קנה, vachachamim
omrim lo kana, it does not take effect. אמר רבה, Amar Raba,
says Raba, מחלוקת בשטר, machlokes beshtar, the debate is when you try
to free a slave with a document, a writ. דרבי סבר והפדה
לא נפדתה, deRabbi savar vehaftay lo niftasah, it says by case of
a man who sleeps with a שפחה, shifcha, with a female slave,
who is והפדה לא נפדתה, vehaftay lo niftasah, has not been fully
redeemed. So that already speaks to this phenomenon of being half redeemed
and half unredeemed, and we're going to try to decide, like, how
do you get to that state? Okay.
מחלוקת בשטר, machlokes beshtar, דרבי סבר והפדה לא נפדתה, deRabbi savar vehaftay
lo niftasah, and פדיון pidyon means with money, not been fully redeemed,
או חפשה לא ניתן לה, o chufshah lo nitan lah, or her
freedom has not been given to her, meaning something that's given as
opposed to the slave paying money to redeem him or herself, something
has, her freedom has not been given, meaning she has not been
freed with a שטר. shtar, So the first part talks about
half freed through money and she has not been fully freed, and
the second part says and she has not been freed with a
שטר, shtar או חפשה לא ניתן לה. o chufshah lo nitan lah.
מקיש שטר לכסף, makish shtar lekesef, it links the שטר shtar to
the money. מה כסף בין כולו בין חציו, ma kesef bein kulo
bein chatziyo, the same way we see by the money, it says
freed but not fully freed, so the same way we see that
the money can, you can achieve half freedom by paying for half
of your value, אף שטר נמי בין כולו בין חציו, af shtar
nami bein kulo bein chatziyo, by the document as well, you can
even give a document and say, by this document I hereby freeing
half of you. That's what רבי says. ורבנן גמירי לה לה מאשה,
verabbanan gemiri lah lah me'ishah, and the rabbis say, no, no, no,
how do we know that a שטר Shtar works at all by
a slave? Because based on this פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* חופשה לא ניתן
לה *chufsha lo nittan lah*, her freedom not given to her, given
to her, and by a woman it says וכתב לה ספר כריתות
*vechatav lah sefer keritut*, he writes for her a writ of divorce.
So we learn out from that link to a גט *get* that
that you can free, the same way a man frees his wife
by a גט *get*, a man frees his slave by a שטר
Shtar, *shtar*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* לה לה מאישה *lah lah me'isha*.
מה אישה חציו לא *mah isha chetzio lo*, and the same way
a man cannot half-divorce his wife, it's an all-or-nothing, right? It's a
personal status issue. So אף עבד נמי חציו לא *af eved nami
chetzio lo*. Even a slave cannot be half. So, what is he
saying? So, put the פסוק *pasuk* aside for a minute. What רבי
*Rebi* is, the way רבא *Rava* is reading this debate is like,
look, he says רבא *Rava*. When it comes to money, money you
can pay off half of your value, and therefore everybody agrees that
that is a way that somebody could become a half-slave half-free person,
they could pay off half of their value. But conceptually a שטר
Shtar *shtar* is different because a שטר Shtar. *shtar*, like we talked
about before about the whole idea of identity, a שטר Shtar *shtar*
starts by focusing not on the question of who owns this person.
A שטר Shtar *shtar* is about your identity. I am hereby making
you a free man. And therefore when you start with ownership and
money, I can pay for half of my value and now I
half-own myself and now maybe I'm a half-free man. But when you
start with a שטר Shtar *shtar*, there there's a debate because a
שטר Shtar. *shtar*, you could say, only works on the whole person.
The same way a גט *get* only defines, it's either the woman
is divorced or not divorced. It's the whole person. A שטר Shtar
*shtar* either makes the slave a free person or not a free
person. It's about their identity, not about their ownership. So that would
be why that would be the Rabbis that said that it's linked
to the גט *get*. And רבי *Rebi* says, no, because it's connected
also to the money. Even a שטר Shtar *shtar* can work halfway.
Okay, so they all agree money works halfway and they debate if
a שטר Shtar *shtar* can work halfway. That's how רבא *Rava* reads
the debate. אבל בכסף *Aval bechesef*,
when it comes to money, דברי הכל קנה *divrei hakol kana*. Everybody
would agree that does work. פדויה ואינה פדויה *Peduya ve'eina peduya*. Okay,
because that would be that והפדה לא נפדתה *vehafpedeh lo nifdatah*. The
woman would be freed but not fully freed. And that's in the
פסוק *pasuk*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לימא בהא קמיפלגי
*Leima beha kamiflagi*. Now, okay, so that's the debate. Now let's, what's
at the core of the debate? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* thinks
maybe it's just a technical issue. לימא בהא קמיפלגי *Leima beha kamiflagi*.
Maybe this is where רבי *Rebi* and the חכמים Hachamim *Chachamim* are
debating. דמר סבר היקש עדיף *demar savar hekesh adif*, that the חכמים
Hachamim *Chachamim* say the היקש *hekesh*, the link of לה לה *lah
lah* to the גט *get* of a woman is stronger than, excuse
me, the היקש *hekesh*, excuse me, the לה לה *lah lah* is
a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*. The היקש *hekesh*, the juxtaposition of the
money to the שטר Shtar *shtar* is stronger than than the גזירה
שוה *gezeirah shavah* of the לה לה *lah lah* to the גט
*get* of the woman. It's pulling in two directions. The חופשה לא
ניתן לה *chufsha lo nittan lah* has a היקש *hekesh* to the
money. It's juxtaposed to the money, which is halfway. But it is
a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* to the גט *get*, which is all
or nothing. So one says the היקש *hekesh* is more powerful and
therefore it connects to the money and it can be halfway. ומר
סבר גזירה שוה עדיפה *umar savar gezeirah shavah adifah*. The גזירה שוה
*gezeirah shavah* is more powerful and therefore it's all or nothing. So
maybe that's their debate. So the גמרא *Gemara* says לא דכולי עלמא
גזירה שוה עדיפה *Lo dechuli alma gezeirah shavah adifah*. I can tell
you that everybody would say we would go by the גזירה שוה
*gezeirah shavah* and we would link it to the גט *get* of
an אשה *isha* and it would be all or nothing. ושאני הכא
דאיכא למיפרך *Veshatni hacha de'ika lemifrach*. That would be all other things
being equal. But the comparison to the גט *get* is not complete.
Why not? מה לאישה שכן אינה יוצאה בכסף *Mah le'isha sheken einah
yotzah bechesef*, because money doesn't work by a woman. So you're not
fully linking the freedom of a slave to a woman because then
you would say a slave couldn't be freed by money. תאמר בעבד
שיוצא בכסף *Tomar be'eved sheyotzei bechesef*. So by a slave who is
freed by money, therefore halfway should work. Okay, so everybody might say
normally we would follow a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*. But here רבי
*Rebi* is going to say, at the end of the day though,
slave is not totally like a woman because money works by a
slave and it doesn't work by a woman, and money works halfway.
So once money works by a slave and that's halfway, even the
גט *get*, even the שטר Shtar, *shtar* can work halfway. And the
Rabbis still say, no, sorry, two different paths, the שטר Shtar *shtar*
works all or nothing. Okay, that's רבי's *Rebi's* explanation. Everybody agrees about
money halfway and the question is שטר Shtar. *shtar*. That makes a
lot of sense.
Okay, רב יוסף אמר *Rav Yosef amar*. Now רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*
has a different interpretation of the debate. מחלוקת בכסף *Machloket bechesef*. No,
actually, he's going to say like this. שטר Shtar? *shtar* everybody agrees
is all or nothing. The question is, can money, can that be
halfway? So that's the issue. The debate is by money. דרבי סבר
והפדה לא נפדתה *DeRebi savar vehafpedeh lo nifdatah*. רבי *Rebi* reads the
פסוק *pasuk* redeemed, not redeemed, meaning פדויה ואינה פדויה *peduya ve'eina peduya*,
half redeemed. So the פסוק *pasuk* is explicit, half redeemed. So רבי
*Rebi* says at least by money it can be halfway. שטר Shtar?
*shtar* I agree is all or nothing. At least by money it
can be halfway. ורבנן סברי דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם *VeRabbanan savri
dibrah Torah kileshon bnei adam*. No, no, no. It just means she
hasn't been redeemed. Like the פסוק *pasuk*... Does it mean you'll be
cleansed but not fully cleansed, or does it mean like the normal
translations have it, you won't be cleansed at all? Okay, so the
חכמים Hachamim say הפדה
לא נפדתה Hifdeh lo nifdatah just means hasn't been redeemed at all,
and the פסוק is talking about a woman that hasn't at all
been redeemed, not half-redeemed. Okay, so according to Rav Yosef,
a שטרא Shtara is all or nothing, and Rebbe though says money
is different, money can be halfway, and the חכמים Hachamim disagree even
with that. Okay, so the debates are mirror images of one another.
Okay, so אבל בשטר דברי הכל לא קנה, Aval beshtar divrei hakol
lo kana, by שטר Shtar everybody would agree it would not work.
Okay, so that's the issue where again that Raba would say, Raba
says that they all agree money is halfway, the question is שטר,
Shtar and Rav Yosef says they all agree שטר Shtar is all
or nothing, the question is can money be halfway? Now, מיתיבי, Meitivei,
I ask you, המשחרר חצי עבדו בשטר. Hamishacher chatzi avdo beshtar. We
have a ברייתא. Braita The ברייתא Braita says if somebody frees half
of his slave with a שטר. Shtar, רבי אומר קנה וחכמים אומרים
לא קנה. Rebbe omer kana vechachamim omrim lo kana. Rebbe says that
it works and the חכמים Hachamim say it doesn't work. So here
explicitly they are debating about whether a שטר Shtar. works halfway. תיובתא
דרב יוסף תיובתא. Tiuvta deRav Yosef tiuvta. That is an absolute contradiction
of Rav Yosef. Rav Yosef said everybody agreed a שטר was all
or nothing, here you see it's not true. Here you see Rebbe
and the חכמים Hachamim debate whether a שטר works halfway. So the
גמרא says נימא לימא בשטר הוא דפליגי אבל בכסף לא
פליגי. Neima leima beshtar hu dephaligi aval bechesef lo phaligi. So now,
בשטר הוא דפליגי אבל בכסף לא פליגי. Beshtar hu dephaligi aval bechesef
lo phaligi. Now what would also sound like is they're only debating
a שטר. Rebbe and the חכמים Hachamim are debating whether a שטר
works halfway. The fact that they're not mentioning money makes it sound
like they all agree that money works halfway. So the simple read
of this ברייתא Braita is exactly like Raba. They debate a שטר
all or nothing or halfway, but implicitly money everybody agrees halfway. So
the גמרא says לימא תהוי תיובתא דרב יוסף בתרתי. Leima tehvei tiuvta
deRav Yosef bitartei. So should I say that this ברייתא Braita not
only proves against Rav Yosef's claim that a
שטר was all or nothing, because here it's explicit they debate whether
a שטר is halfway, maybe the ברייתא Braita also contradicts Rav Yosef's
claim that they debate about money? Because this ברייתא makes it sound,
by only talking about a שטר, it makes it sound that they
all agree by money. So does that contradict the second part of
Rav Yosef's claim? So the גמרא says אמר לך רב יוסף פליגי
בשטר והוא הדין בכסף. Amar lach Rav Yosef phaligi beshtar vehu hadin
bechesef. No, no, no.
You've proven to me that they debate whether a שטר is halfway
or all or nothing, that it is a debate by a שטר.
But I will still claim that they're also debating money. They don't
agree by the money part. Okay, they debate both. That Rebbe says
everything works halfway and the חכמים say nothing works halfway. Okay, so
that's what at least I'm going to try to salvage that part
of my position. If that's true,
והאי דקמיפלגי בשטר, Veha dekamiphalgi beshtar, so then why are they only
discussing the שטר? If they debate whether both of them work, either
of them work halfway, why don't they also talk about the money?
Why are they only talking about the שטר? להודיעך כוחו דרבי. Lehodiecha
kocho deRebbe. To show you the power of Rebbe. That Rebbe who
says halfway, not only halfway by money which makes sense, but even
halfway by a שטר which would seem to talk about the whole
identity of the person, Rebbe is going to go so far to
say even a שטר works halfway. But just because they're discussing by
a שטר does not mean that they agree by money. The חכמים
don't like money halfway either. So the גמרא says וליפלוג בכסף להודיעך
כוחם דרבנן. Veliphalog bechesef lehodiecha kocham derabbanan. So why not discuss the
money issue and show you that the rabbis who say it doesn't
work, say not only does it not work halfway by שטר, it
doesn't even work halfway by money? So the גמרא says the answer
that we could have expected, כוח דהיתירא עדיף ליה. Koach deheteira adif
leh. The power of being permitting is more powerful. Meaning, it's always
easier to say it doesn't work. Oh, this isn't a perfect freedom,
so it's not going to work. Everything's got to be perfect, it's
got to be 100%, 50% doesn't work. So okay, the חכמים don't
want it to work halfway even by money, that's fine. But it's
a much bigger חידוש Chiddush by Rebbe to say I'm ready to
say it works halfway, it doesn't have to be perfect, it doesn't
have to be all, and not only does it work halfway by
money, it even works halfway by שטר. So we'd rather tell you
the power of Rebbe's position over the fact that the rabbis don't
like it even by כסף. Kesef. Okay, we will stop here.